SHUBHAM MEHTA

Mechanical Engineer



SUMMARY

Mechanical engineer with a passion for tech and a knack for leading both machines and teams. With 2+ years of experience, I've built robots, led teams, and even convinced a drone to beat the wind. I'm all about blending creativity with technology, believing the best ideas come from collaboration. Looking ahead, I aim to push the boundaries of innovation, lead impactful projects, and maybe inspire the next generation of tech enthusiasts along the way.

EXPERIENCE

Technical operations lead

Encora Air Pvt. Ltd

= 03/2024 - 08/2024

Mumbai, India

Technical operations lead.

- · Lead daily operations of the technical department.
- · Planned and coordinated technical processes with cross-functional teams.
- Ensured compliance with industry regulations and safety standards.
- · Managed troubleshooting and provided hands-on technical support.
- Analyzed performance data for operational efficiency and continuous improvement.

Robotics Designer

- · Designed solar panel cleaning robots (Autonomous and Manual).
- · Customized designs as per the client's requirements.
- Collaborated with the Electronics and Manufacturing team, guiding them through the entire process.

Drone Pilot and Aviation Research Intern

Flyo Eduventures Pvt. Ltd

iii 09/2022 - 01/2023

m 07/2022 - 08/2022

Drone Pilot and Aviation Research Intern.

- · Designed and fabricated a medical drone.
- · Tested various drone frames.
- · Conducted researches based on an aerial survey.

Robotics Instructor and Human resources assistant

Brainlox

- Robotics Instructor and Human resources assistant.

 Coached robotics to students aged 12-22 years.
- · Managed and scheduled lectures as part of the HR team.
- Conducted doubt sessions regarding robotics and technology.
- · Conducted **onboarding** sessions for newly joined interns.

Digital Marketing Intern

Viral Fission

04/2019 - 05/2020

Digital Marketing Intern.

- Conducted market-based research for brands like JioSaavn, OnePlus, Myntra, Vice and Times Network.
- \cdot Learned graphic designing softwares, $\textbf{Adobe\ Photoshop}$ and $\textbf{Adobe\ Illustrator}.$
- Managed the database of these brands and represented it in the form of Gantt charts and graphs using Tableau and Power Bi.

EDUCATION

MBA in Technology Management

Tuhh's Northern Institute of Technology Management

2024 - Present ♥ Hamburg, Germany

Bachelor Of Technology in Mechanical Engineering

Dwarkadas J. Sanghvi College of engineering

KEY ACHIEVEMENTS

Q

Winner of European Rover Challenge

Won **1st place** internationally at the European Rover Challenge after winning four of five tasks.

Q

Second position at DJS Nirmiti's Project competition

Ranked **second position** at DJS Nirmiti's Project competition for designing a biomimetic inspired VTOL UAV.

•

Grand Finalist at CopterHack'22

Secured **1st rank** in Asia and **7th rank** worldwide in CopterHack'22.



Winner of Electronics' eQuiz competition
Awarding Institution

Won this quiz with **96%**, edging out **40** competitors from the state.

PROJECTS

Structural Analysis of a Drone Frame

07/2022 - 09/2022

Structural analysis of a drone frame to determine the best material.

- Analyzed a drone frame for optimum material selection using Ansys 2020.
- Material selection was based on material properties like Tensile Strength, Modulus of Rigidity, Stiffness, and its behavior to loads like Deformation and Stress values

Design and Fabrication of bird inspired VTOL UAV

= 2022 - 2023

The project entails creating an aircraft that mimics bird flight mechanics.

- The design process involves studying the biomimetic model's aerodynamics, analyzing its flight characteristics, and creating a 3D CAD model.
- The goal of a biomimetic VTOL UAV is to improve flight agility, maneuverability, and efficiency for aerial surveying and search and rescue operations.

Air ambulance

= 04/2020 - 06/2020

Development of a medical drone for rapid victim aid.

- Introduced a drone medical application for swift delivery of aid.
- Autonomous operation eliminates the need for pilots.
- Equipped with a monitor for direct communication with doctors

Vertical Wind turbine

= 03/2019 - 04/2019

Vertical wind turbine project.

- Designed a portable vertical wind turbine that can produce power in any weather because of its mobility.
- · Lightweight design for diverse usage scenarios.

PASSIONS



Founder and Captain of DJS Astra

I formed and led a team of 25 to compete in **combat robotics**, gaining hand-on experirnce in the field. We built three robots in different weight categories: 8kg, 15kg, 30kg.



Captain of DJS Phoenix

I mentored a team of 15 in designing and competing with **autonomous and racing drones**, successfully building four drones and winning prestigious competitions like COEX, IDRL, and iMAV.

CERTIFICATION

G-Suite Administration Specialization

G-Suite Administration Specialization

MATLAB: On Ramp

Certificate in MATLAB: Onramp

Virtual Reality

University of London - Coursera

LANGUAGES

Gujarati	Native	••••
English	Native	••••
Hindi	Proficient	••••
German	Beginner	• • • • •

SKILLS

SolidWorks	Adobe Photoshop		Ansys	
Robotics	G-Suite	Office-365	Matlab	
Teamwork	Leaders	hip Inquisi	tiveness	
Time management Effective communication				